## Lucy L. Gao

## Ph.D. Candidate in Biostatistics

Email: lucygao at uw dot edu Website: lucylgao dot com

I am a Canadian researcher working in the areas of statistical machine learning, applied optimization, and experiment design. I am interested in tackling problems in complex data settings, such as multi-view data, network data, compositional data, and spatial data.

### Education

SEPTEMBER 2015 - JUNE 2020 (EXPECTED)

#### University of Washington, Seattle WA - Ph.D. Biostatistics

- Dissertation: Hypothesis Testing with Multiple Data Views
- Committee: Marina Meila, Ali Shojaie, Cole Trapnell, and Daniela Witten (Chair)

SEPTEMBER 2011 - JUNE 2015

University of Victoria, Victoria BC - B.Sc. Honours Mathematics and Statistics

# **Work Experience**

JULY 2018 - SEPTEMBER 2018

LinkedIn Co, Sunnyvale CA - Data Scientist Intern, Experimentation Science

• Developed new experiment designs to increase the sensitivity of experiments on the in-house experimentation platform.

## **Publications**

Statistical Methodology

#### <u>Published or Accepted:</u>

- Gao, L. L., Bien, J. and Witten, D. (2019) Are clusterings of multiple data views independent? Biostatistics, kxz001, https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxz001. [Won a 2019 ASA Biometrics Section Travel Award.]
- 2. **Gao, L. L.** and Zhou, J. (2017) D-optimal designs based on the second-order least squares estimator. *Statistical Papers*, 58(1), 77-94.
- 3. **Gao, L. L.** and Zhou, J. (2014) New optimal design criteria for regression models with asymmetric errors. *Journal of Statistical Planning and Inference*, 149, 140-151. [A video based on this paper was a finalist in the SSC Statistics on Reels video competition.]

#### **Submitted Preprints:**

1. Liu, P., **Gao, L.L.** and Zhou, J. (2020+) R-optimal designs for multi-response regression models with multi-factors, submitted to *Communications in Statistics - Theory and Methods*. Preprint available at http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02539.

- 2. **Gao, L.L.** and Zhou, J. (2020+) Minimax D-optimal designs for multivariate regression models with multi-factors, submitted to *Journal of Statistical Planning and Inference*. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.00745.
- 3. **Gao, L.L.,** Witten, D. and Bien, J. (2020+) Testing for association in multi-view network data, submitted to *Biometrics*. Preprint available at <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.11640">https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.11640</a>. [Won a 2020 ASA Statistical Learning and Data Science Section Student Paper Award.]

#### **Statistical Applications**

1. Hsu, E. K., Shaffer, M. L., **Gao, L.**, Sonnenday, C., Volk, M. L., Bucuvalas, J. and Lai, J. C. (2017) Analysis of liver offers to pediatric candidates on the transplant wait list. *Gastroenterology*, 153(4), 988-995. [Received an editorial in *Gastroenterology*.]

## **Presentations**

### **Invited Presentations**

- (January 2020) "Statistical inference for multi-view clustering" for the University of Waterloo Department of Statistics and Acturial Science department seminar series, in Waterloo, O.N., Canada.
- (December 2019) "Statistical inference for multi-view clustering" for the McGill University
  Department of Mathematics and Statistics department seminar series, in Montreal, Q.C.,
  Canada.
- 3. (September 2018) "Are clusterings of multiple data views independent?" for the University of Victoria Department of Statistics department seminar series, in Victoria, B.C., Canada.
- 4. (July 2018) "Are clusterings of multiple data views independent?" at the 2018 Joint Statistical Meetings, in Vancouver, B.C., Canada.

## **Contributed Presentations**

- 1. (August 2019) "Are clusterings of multiple data views independent?" at the 2019 Joint Statistical Meetings, in Denver, Colorado.
- 2. (June 2019) "Testing for association in multi-view network data" at the 2019 WNAR Annual Meeting of IBC (International Biometric Conferences), in Portland, Oregon.
- 3. (December 2017) "Are clusterings of multiple data views independent?" at AT&T Graduate Student Symposium, in New York City, New York.
- 4. (September 2016) "Distributionally robust multinomial regression" at BIRS Robustness Theory and Methodology: Recent Advances and Future Directions workshop, in Banff, A.B., Canada.
- 5. (August 2015) "D-optimal designs based on the second-order least squares estimator" at the 2015 Joint Statistical Meetings, in Seattle, Washington.
- 6. (May 2014) "New optimal design criteria for regression models with asymmetric errors" at the Statistical Society of Canada (SSC) Student Conference, in Toronto, Ontario.

# **Awards and Scholarships**

- (2020) ASA Statistical Learning and Data Science Section Student Paper Award, valued at \$1250 USD
- (2019) ASA Biometrics Section Travel Award, valued at \$1,000 USD
- (2016-2019) **NSERC PGSD-3**, a doctoral scholarship from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Council of Canada, valued at \$21,000 CAD/year for 3 years
- (2015) CIHR Summer Studentship Award, an undergraduate research award from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, valued at \$6,250 CAD
- (2014) NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award, valued at \$5,625 CAD
- (2013) **NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award**, valued at \$5,625 CAD

# **Teaching Experience**

MARCH 2019, University of Washington, Seattle

### Guest Lecturer for STAT 435: Introduction to Statistical Machine Learning

- STAT 435 is a class targeted at undergraduate students majoring in statistics.
- Gave a guest lecture on unsupervised learning methods.

MARCH 2019, University of Washington, Seattle

### Guest Lecturer for STAT 546: Machine Learning for Biomedical and Public Health

- STAT 546 is a class targeted at graduate students in the School of Public Health.
- Gave a guest lecture on unsupervised learning methods.

June 2018, University of Washington, Seattle

#### **Guest Lecturer for BIOST 311: Regression Methods in the Health Sciences**

- BIOST 311 is a class targeted at undergraduate students in the School of Public Health.
- Gave a guest lecture introducing regression methods for correlated data.

April 2018-June 2018, University of Washington, Seattle

### **Teaching Assistant for BIOST 310: Biostatistics in the Health Sciences**

- BIOST 310 is a class targeted at undergraduate students in the School of Public Health.
- Taught discussion/tutorial sections once a week, held office hours, and graded assignments.
- Developed material for discussion/tutorial sections.

July 2017, University of Washington, Seattle

#### Teaching Assistant for the UW Summer Institutes in Big Data

• Provided teaching support for the 2-day unsupervised learning module.

# **Service**

Reviewer for Biostatistics, Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics, Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C, and Electronic Journal of Statistics

(2017-2018) UW Peer Mentoring Program Member

(2017-2018) Co-organizer for UW Biostatistics working groups (Witten Lab and SLAB Lab)

## **Software**

multiviewtest, R Package on CRAN